Wendell, Mass. Congregational Church records, 1783-1955.
Congregational Library & Archives
Wendell, Mass. Congregational Church records, 1783-1955.
RG4890
Congregational Library & Archives
1.13 Cubic Feet
(2 boxes)
The Congregational Church of Wendell was formed in Wendell, Mass. on November 29, 1774. The Wendell, Mass. Congregational Church records document the history, administration, and life of the church and its members from its inception through the 1950s. Types of records present include extensive financial records, church and society meeting minutes, correspondence, and important earyy vital statistics for the church and its members.
Congregational Church (Wendell, Mass.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Records received in 2004. No additional acquisition information is available for this collection.
Accruals
Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.
Historical Note
The Congregational Church of Wendell was formed in Wendell, Mass. on November 29, 1774. The first meeting house was built in 1783, and a second in 1846. Throughout the collection the church is referred to by several names, including Church of Christ, First Church, Central Congregational Church in Wendell, and the Congregational Church of Wendell. The Trustees of the Ministerial Fund of the First Congregational Society in Wendell were incorporated in 1823 to carry out their function for the church. A copy of the articles of their incorporation is pasted inside the front cover of their minute book. On December 2, 1874 the church and the town of Wendell celebrated their centennial with a joint event.
Even though the church was relatively small throughout its history, the Congregational Church of Wendell contributed to domestic and foreign missions, including mission work in China. The church belonged to the Franklin Association of Congregational Churches and worked closely with the Massachusetts Home Missionary Society to call and fund its ministers. In later years the church shared its minister with a church in the nearby town of Erving. In the course of its history, the Congregational Church in Wendell had many different ministers. Rev. Edmund Blackmer is documented more thoroughly than any other minister that served the church because of a nervous disorder that forced him to delay accepting the church's call for almost two full years, from the fall of 1918 to the spring of 1920. Another minister of note is Rev. Harlan P. Metcalf, who died in the office of minister, leaving behind the text of a sermon intended to be preached on Mother's Day, included in this collection. Also worthy of note is Mrs. Effie Bowen, who served as the clerk of the Congregational Church in Wendell for more than 30 years in the early 1900s.
The Congregational Church of Wendell joined the United Church of Christ in 1964 and folded in 2004.
Scope and Contents
The Wendell, Mass. Congregational Church records document the history, administration, and life of the church and its members from its inception through the 1950s. This collection includes financial material in many forms, including ledger and treasury books, account books, receipts and correspondence from individuals and agencies. Records of church business and personnel are preserved in formal record books, minute books, loose records and correspondence. Correspondence includes letters of dismissal and acceptance of congregants, letters from ministers accepting and relinquishing their posts and letters to the church clerk.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series, the first of which has been further arranged into five sub-series. Each series and subseries has been arranged chronologically by start date, when possible, and, further, by topic.
Series 1: Parish Records and Personnel, 1783-1953
Subseries 1: Church and Society Records, 1783-1953
Subseries 2: Vital Statistics, 1812-1949
Subseries 3: Pastoral records, 1886-1947
Subseries 4: Church Services, 1910-1953
Subseries 5: Church and Town History, 1854-1950
Series 2: Church Finances, 1820-1955
Technical Requirements
To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari 5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.
Baptismal records.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Marriage records.; New England's Hidden Histories.; Registers of births, etc.; Sermons, American.; Congregational Church (Wendell, Mass.); Wendell (Mass.) -- Church history.
- Parish records and personnel, 1783 1953; 1783-1953; 24 Files; (3 volumes, 21 folders)
  Scope and Contents
  The Parish and Personnel records cover the administrative, personnel, and written history of the Congregational Church of Wendell and its environs. Types of materials present include personal and official correspondence, vital statistics such as membership certificates, baptismal records, and records of death, society minutes, resignations, and historical sketches of the town of Wendell.
  - Church and Society records, 1783 1953; 1783-1953; 10 Files; (3 volumes, 6 folders)
    The Church and Society records cover official church business such as church correspondence and meeting minutes. Types of materials present include annual meeting minutes, church correspondence, ecclesiastical council minutes, baptismal records, death records, marriage records, Society minutes, general and parish meeting minutes, and administrative documents.
    - Records of the First Church in Wendell, 1783 1847; 1783-1847 (Box 1, Volume 1)
      Digital Copies
      These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories project. Digital reproductions are available to view online.
      The Records of the First Church in Wendell is the first of two bound volumes of handwritten records that cover a broad range of topics related to the administration of the church as well as the happenings of the church ministers and members. Types of materials present in the volume include records related to the creation of a "religious Profession," meeting minutes, records of votes, a list of founding members of the church, records of birth, records of admission, records from the deacons, records of dismission, baptismal records, marriage records, records of death, public confessions of guilt, annual birth and death statistics, church contributions, and copies of church correspondence.
    - Records of the First Church in Wendell, 1847 1910; 1847-1910 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    - First Congregational Society in Wendell minutes, 1823 1946; 1823-1946 (Box 1, Volume 3)
    - Minutes, meetings, and confrences, 1891 1905; 1891-1905 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence regarding annual meetings, 1901 1910; 1901-1910 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - General incoming correspondence, 1904 1940; 1904-1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence from China Mission and donations, 1907 1926; 1907-1926 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - General business, resignations, deaths, 1921 1933; 1921-1933 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence regarding geneological searches at Wendell, 1938 1940; 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Vital statistics, 1858 1949; 1858-1949; 4 Folders
    The Vital Statistics of the Congregational Church of Wendell include church membership records, certificates of membership and dismission, and baptismal records.
    - Letters of dismission and acceptance of church members, 1858 1911; 1858-1911 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Letters of dismission and acceptance of church members, 1912 1949; 1912-1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Church membership, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Baptismal records, 1917 1941; 1917-1941 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Pastoral records, 1886 1947; 1886-1947; 6 Folders
    The Pastoral records cover the official and personal records of the ministers of the Congregational Church of Wendell. Types of materials present include official summons, pastoral correspondence, pastoral calls, letters of resignation, and missionary correspondence.
    - Summons to Ecclesiastical Council, 1886 1941; 1886-1941 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence from Massachusetts Home Missionary Society, 1908 1926; 1908-1926 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence of Pastoral Calls and Resignations, 1908 1919; 1908-1919 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence of Pastoral Calls and Resignations, 1923 1947; 1923-1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Rev. Edmund F. Blackmer Correspondence with Wendell, 1918 1920; 1918-1920 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence to Rev. Arthur Green regarding 100th Anniversary Celebration, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Church services, 1910 1953; 1910-1953; 3 Folders
    The Church Services records include a booklet for lawyers of church organizations, the published constitution of the Franklin Association, a Mother's Day sermon, and Sunday Service pamphlets.
    - Booklets, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Rev. Harlan P. Metcalf Mother's Day sermon, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Order of service, 1940-1953 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Church and town history, 1854 1950; 1854-1950; 2 Folders
    The Church and Town History records cover historical sketches and other documents related to the history of the town of Wendell and the Congregational Church of Wendell. Types of materials present include brief historical sketches, historical records from the clerk, and a typed manuscript for the 150th anniversary of the church.
    - Historical sketches, 1854 1939; 1854-1939 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Wendell 150 Years Old, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Church finances, 1820 1955; 1820-1955; 18 Files; (14 volumes, 4 folders)
  The Church Finances records cover the extensive financial documents of the Congregational Church of Wendell. Types of materials present include church ledgers, treasury records, collection records, grants, assessment records, account records, and promissory notes.
  - Wendell Parish treasury book, 1822 1838; 1822-1838 (Box 2)
    The Parish Treasury Book is a hardbound volume of financial records for the Congregational Church of Wendell. Types of materials present within the volume include finance committee reports, account balances, records of transactions, salary records, and tax records.
  - Central Congregational Church of Wendell account book, 1823 1875; 1823-1875 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  - Central Congregational Church of Wendell account book, 1895 1899; 1895-1899 (Box 1, Volume 5)
  - Central Congregational Church of Wendell account book, 1899 1903; 1899-1903 (Box 1, Volume 6)
  - Central Congregational Church of Wendell account book, 1903 1907; 1903-1907 (Box 1, Volume 7)
  - Central Congregational Church of Wendell account book, 1907 1912; 1907-1912 (Box 1, Volume 8)
  - Central Congregational Church of Wendell promissory notes, undated (Box 1, Volume 9)
  - Communion Service Collectors account book, 1837 1936; 1837-1936 (Box 1, Volume 10)
  - Wendell Parish treasury book, 1854 1896; 1854-1896 (Box 1, Volume 11)
  - First Congregational Society in Wendell accounts, 1896 1921; 1896-1921 (Box 1, Volume 12)
  - Church account book, 1921 1939; 1921-1939 (Box 1, Volume 13)
  - Central Congregational Church of Wendell mission funds collected and paid, 1893 1955; 1893-1955 (Box 1, Volume 14)
  - Ledger of pledges and collections, 1913 1924; 1913-1924 (Box 1, Volume 15)
  - Parsonage account book, 1938 1945; 1938-1945 (Box 1, Volume 16)
  - Donation receipts and financial correspondence, 1892 1941; 1892-1925, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Ministerial grants, 1920 1942; 1920-1942 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Franklin Association of Congregational Churches assessments, 1924 1934; 1924-1934 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Collection records, 1936 1941; 1936-1941 (Box 1, Folder 25)